Hi, everyone. My name
is Dr. Joseph Holloway,
and in this session,
we're going to
be discussing inflammatory
heart disease.
Now, inflammatory heart
disease takes into account
all the layers of the
heart. So we're going to be
discussing endocarditis,
myocarditis, and pericarditis.
We'll describe the
etiologies for each one, the
clinical presentation
that you would expect, and
how you could diagnose
each one of those, in
addition to mentioning some
of the related clinical
forms of inflammatory
heart disease as well.
All right, so we're
going to start here
with endocarditis,
which should be a
bit of a review from
a previous lecture.
So endocarditis is the
inflammation of the
heart's internal lining,
which is the endocardium.
And of course, that takes
into account the valves as
well. And the most frequent
valve that's going to be
involved and colonized is
going to be the mitral valve
on the left side of the heart,
and then that's followed
by the aortic valve. Very
infrequently are you going
to see valves on the right
side of the heart involved,
like the tricuspid valve,
and that would really
only be associated with the
risk factor of IV drug use.
All right, so speaking
of risk factors,
yes, certainly IV drug
use would be a risk factor
for right-sided endocarditis,
specifically associated
with the tricuspid
valve. But certainly age
is a big risk factor,
which should make sense
because as individuals age,
oftentimes there's more
of a need for the insertion
of prosthetic devices.
Um,
oral manipulation is a
big risk factor, right?
And so that would allow
for, um, your normal oral
flora, uh, portal of
entry to gain access into
your bloodstream and, uh,
any sort of history of,
um, heart issues, right?
So, uh, preexisting
infections, any sort of
structural issues or congenital
issues, uh, and any
sort of, um, history of
surgical procedures that
you have with your heart.
All right. Now, what we're
going to do is just kind
of touch on and remind you
about the pathogenesis of
endocarditis. So there's
basically two things at
play here. Number one, you
need some sort of preexisting
injury, endothelial injury,
that's going to allow
for the exposure of
subendothelial matrix proteins.
And when you have that,
what's going to occur is
going to be the attachment
of serum proteins and
platelets creating a
thrombus in that location.
Now, second to that, you
need transient bacteremia,
right? So you need some
sort of microbe in the blood
that then has the ability
to attach to that thrombus.
And so once that occurs,
now you have a population of
microbes, generally bacteria,
that are now dividing.
That's going to recruit
even more serum proteins,
immune proteins, platelets
to that location, creating
this expanding structure
known as a vegetation. And
it's that vegetation then
that has the ability to
obviously disrupt the tissue,
destroy the tissue, and
also will impair the
functionality of the valve. And
that's where you get the
new murmur or the valvular
regurgitation that's
associated with endocarditis.
And of course, you could
also then have little parts
of that vegetation break off
and become septic emboli.
So that can happen on the
right side of the heart
and become a pulmonary
embolism. And it can also happen
on the left side of the
heart. And if that occurs,
basically the embolism
can go basically
anywhere in systemic
circulation.
so what we're going to do
is take a brief look at some
of the main groups of
bacteria and microbes that
cause ie and of course
you have to start with the
staphylococci so both staph
aureus and staph epidermidis so
staph aureus by itself is
responsible for approximately
somewhere in the order
of about 30% of all cases
of IE, in addition to
generally being the case that
the cause of any acute case
of IE as well. And the reason
for that is due to its
virulence factors. So it has
the potential uniquely
to be able to bind to non
-injured healthy endothelial
cells or healthy heart valves.
And it does that using
surface level binding
proteins. So the binding
proteins known as fibronectin
binding proteins that can
actually attach to healthy
endothelial cells. And once
that happens, it also uses a
second surface level binding
protein known as clumping
factor that could then
recruit serum proteins like
fibrin and platelets as
well to be able to start
creating a vegetation from
scratch. So that is basically
how you can take a healthy
heart valve and start the
endocarditis picture using
specifically staph aureus.
Now being able to differentiate
the causative agent
of IE one from the other
is going to be important
biochemically and the way
that you do that is first with
the catalase test. So catalase
is going to be the way
that you differentiate the
staph group from the strep
group and both of those
groups are really the main
causative agents of most cases
of IE. So the staph group
is going to be catalase
positive, whereas the strep
group tends to be catalase
negative. So a really easy
way that you can biochemically
differentiate those.
Now within the staph group
itself, the way that you
can tell the difference
between aureus and epidermidis
is going to be by a coagulase
test. So coagulase is a
secreted enzyme that's
generated by staph aureus. It's
very close to clumping
factor, and it does basically
the same thing. It will
recruit serum proteins like
fibrin and platelets as
well to be able to coat the
bacterial cells and shield
them from the immune response.
And so that is kind of a
unique virulence factor
for staph aureus and
allows you to differentiate
it from epidermidis. And
you can see that test in
the tubes in the picture
down below. Whereas staph
epi, the blood serum
stays liquid versus staph
aureus, which creates a
clump with the blood serum.
Now, staph epi by itself
also has the ability
to cause endocarditis,
but usually is associated
with a subacute picture,
and it's also associated
with prosthetic valves.
That really stems
from the type of capsule
that it makes that
allows it to adhere to
those types of substrates.
that brings us to streptococcus
and the first example
here is the strep viridens
group so that's a group
of streptococci that are
part of your normal oral
flora so species like strep
sanguinous mitus mutans
among others now the way
to differentiate between
strep and staph like I
said is by using a catalase
test, and streps are going
to be catalase negative.
And if you consider strep
as the causative agent
of IE, you want to start
thinking about some
sort of oral trauma,
some sort of dental
procedure that was done
that allowed for a portal
of entry for the bacteria
into the bloodstream.
And when the viridin's
species cause IE, generally
they are going to create
a subacute picture. And
in fact, viridin's streps
are the most common
cause of subacute IE. So
when they are attaching to
a heart valve or some
damaged endothelial cells,
they're going to do that
by utilizing dextran
secretion. So in the same
way dextrans are going to
mediate the creation of
plaque biofilm in the mouth,
that's the same way that
they could attach to a
damaged heart valve and
start to create a vegetation
because of the adherence
mediated by dextran.
Now, the other example is
Streptococcus galliliticus.
Now, that used to be
called Streptococcus bovis.
Same thing,
same type of bacterium,
just a different name. But
this is not part of
the oral flora. So this
specifically is an inhabitant
of the GI tract. And so
if you see strep galliiticus
causing an infection
in the heart, it has to
have come from the GI
tract. And so there is a
strong association with
other pathology in the
colon. So if that's the cause
and that's identified,
you would certainly want
to follow up with a
colonoscopy for your patient.
Related to strep is going
to be the enterococcus
group. And so you're
going to find some of the
same basic features as you
would see in strep. All
right, so you're going to
have gram-positive cocci.
They're going to be
arranged in short chains.
It's also catalase negative,
which allows you to
differentiate it from
the staph group as well.
Now, endococcus is going to
be a little bit more aligned
with strep galliliticus
insofar as it is a gut
bacterial species, in addition
to being found in the GU
tract. So you could then
differentiate your enterococcus
and strep galliticus
examples from the viridens
group by running a bile
escalon test. And you can see
that in the picture on the
slide. So as escalon is
hydrolyzed, it will change
the medium from kind of an
orangey yellow color to a black
color which would indicate
a positive test now of
course you can further
subdivide enterococcus and
strep galliiticus by either
running a pyr test or growing
in a high salt environment
and both of those enterococcus
would be positive for
So that leaves us with the
atypical causes of IEE,
otherwise known as the
culture negative microbes.
And that could be the
case because of a number
of different reasons.
Either the microbes
are fastidious, or
they're intracellular, or
they just take a long
time to grow on a medium.
So we could loosely
categorize them
into gram-negative
and gram-positive.
From the gram-negative
category, you could pick
out the Hossack group,
right? So that's responsible
for somewhere in the order
of about 3% of all IE.
It is also part of the
normal oral flora for
people. So you could think
about that basically in
terms of the way that
you think about the strep
viridens group, right? So
same portal of entry and
access to the bloodstream.
The only difference
would be that the Hossack
group would take a long
time to grow on media
versus the Viridin's group
that would grow in, you
know, 24 to 48 hours.
Coxiella burnetii, which
happens to be the most
common cause of culture
negative, i.e., happens to be
difficult because it is
an intracellular microbe,
right? Or if we take a look
at the gram positive category,
NVS, right? So NVS is
very similar in scope
to the strep viridin's
group, but happens
to need to be supplemented
with vitamin B6.
And of course, there's the
fungal causes, the most
common of which would be
candida and aspergillus.
So what would we expect to
see in a patient with IE?
Well, first, there should
be a heart murmur, right?
So that would be brought
about by a vegetation
that's now disrupting the
functioning of the valve.
But you would also expect
there to be some systemic
symptoms due to just
generalized inflammation, and
that's where you would
see symptoms like a fever,
which most individuals
with IE would display, in
addition to things like chills
or malaise, fatigue, weight
loss, things like that. You
might also see petechiae,
right, based on the
damage to the small blood
vessels in the capillaries
due to the inflammation.
Now, the other things
listed there are going to be
very much connected to
IE, although you wouldn't
necessarily see them
within patients all that
frequently. So the first is
Roth spots, which are retinal
hemorrhages that have a
particular clearing in
the middle of them, brought
about by septic emboli.
Likewise, Janeway
lesions and splinter
hemorrhages also
of the nail bed are
brought about by
septic emboli as well.
And of course, then there's
the Osler's nodes, which
are kind of very tender,
painful, swelling or lesions
that you would find on
the fingers and the toes.
Now, those are not
necessarily brought about
by septic emboli, but
instead are due to
a hypersensitivity
reaction and the deposition
of immune complexes
at those locations.
Now, as a reminder, the
system of diagnosis of IE
follows the modified major
and minor DUKE criteria, and
the combinations of those
are presented on the slide.
So the minor criteria
revolve around some of the
signs and symptoms that
we just talked about,
in addition to the risk
factors that are associated
with IE. And the major
criteria have to do
with either culturing a
microbe from the blood or
identifying a vegetation
on an echocardiogram.
So if you have a patient
that has bacteremia
and has a valvular
vegetation identified on
echo, that basically
confirms endocarditis.
But of course, it's
possible to have one without
the other. So if you
have a patient that has
bacteremia but doesn't have
any evidence of a valvular
vegetation, then it's
pretty broad where that
infection can be coming
from, right? So you can
consider a whole host of
different possibilities.
Certainly in a non
-exhaustive list, you know,
you can consider an
intravascular catheter,
a prosthetic joint.
There's a whole bunch
of reasons why you
might have an infection.
in terms of having a
valvular vegetation but no
bacteremia well then you
might be in a situation where
you have a true case of
non-bacterial thrombotic
endocarditis or perhaps you
have a different type of
condition like antiphospholipid
syndrome which is characterized
by clotting systemic
clotting of the blood so
the workup for a patient
would start with a history
and physical and if there's
a new murmur you might want
to order an ECG or perhaps
a urinalysis and that's
because approximately half
the cases of IE have some
sort of proteinuria or
hematuria associated with it.
In terms of lab work maybe
getting a full blood count
would be good, a metabolic
panel or running some tests
to try to assess the speed
of clotting of the blood.
In addition to taking blood
cultures, right, because
you would want to be able
to culture the microbes
that are causing the IE. So
two sets would be standard,
but three would be preferable,
especially if there's
been some sort of antibiotic
administered earlier.
Imaging is also important,
right? So you can utilize
a transthoracic echocardiogram
or a transesophageal
echocardiogram, which is
going to give a little
bit better resolution,
has a little bit more
sensitivity to it. But
either one of those would be
acceptable to identify
and confirm a valvular
vegetation and help with
the diagnosis. Now, if you
can confirm a case of IE,
oftentimes you would then
choose to treat it with
some type of antibiotic.
So that would depend on
the type of bacterial cause
that was the source of the
IE. And of course, there's
always the surgical option,
and that would depend
on the extent of how
damaged the valve would be.
All right, so before
we finish up our talk
on endocarditis, I
just wanted to touch
on morantic endocarditis,
which is the non
-bacterial thrombotic
form of endocarditis.
So in this situation, it
basically mirrors what
happens in infective
endocarditis, where you have to
have some sort of endothelial
injury, and then the
accumulation of serum
proteins and platelets at
that location, producing a
vegetation or a thrombus.
But in this case, the thrombus
is going to be sterile.
There's no microbial
population associated with it.
Now, individuals that might
have this generally are
going to have some sort
of hypercoagulable state.
So it's associated with
different varieties of
advanced malignancies like
certain types of cancers
or certain types of autoimmune
diseases like lupus.
Specifically, Libman
-Sacks endocarditis is a
complication of lupus
where you get deposition
of immune complexes on
the heart valves. Or
it could just be a
situation like pregnancy.
Now, individuals that have
morantic endocarditis,
they can be asymptomatic,
but ultimately the
complications can be the same
as infective endocarditis,
where the thrombus has the
potential to have little
parts of it break off
and become septic emboli,
just like you would see
in infective endocarditis.
All right, so we're going
to move on to myocarditis
here, which is an inflammation
of the heart muscle,
the myocardium, along with
myocyte necrosis. Now,
this was also recently
relevant during the COVID
-19 pandemic, where a very
small number of COVID-19
vaccine recipients showed
mild forms and mild symptoms
of myocarditis. Now,
it's not fully understood
why that was the case,
but the transient symptoms
were likely just brought
about by individual pro
-inflammatory signaling causing
the heart inflammation.
Now, there's a number
of different reasons why
myocarditis can arise, but
the first thing to mention
here is that approximately
50% of all cases are
idiopathic with the causative
agent going unidentified.
Now, of course, there are
some definitive causes for
myocarditis infection would
be one and that could be a
whole host of different
infective agents toxins as well
so you could imagine alcohol
abuse or illicit drug
use things like cocaine
or amphetamines different
varieties of chemotherapeutic
agents so cancer treatments,
antipsychotics, or
even environmental
toxins. So exposure
to carbon monoxide
or different varieties
of heavy metals.
You could also consider
immunologic responses, right?
So allergic responses,
things like hypersensitivity
reactions to something
like penicillin, or you
could consider more systemic
disorders like lupus or
celiac disease, Crohn disease,
things of that nature.
And, of course,
physical agents as
well can bring
about myocarditis,
so pretty severe
electric shock,
radiation treatment
for certain cancers,
or even just simple blunt
force trauma to the chest.
All right, so we're going
to take a look at some of
the main microbial causes
of myocarditis, and the main
cause is really going to
be dictated by location.
So in North America and
Europe, the main cause is
generally going to be
viral, so a whole host of
different viruses that can
cause the inflammation.
Some of the main ones are
noted on the slide here.
So parvovirus or enteroviruses
like Coxsackievirus B,
adenoviruses, SARS
-CoV-2, among others.
Now, you would
imagine if you have a
viral infection in
your myocytes, that's
going to evoke an
immune response.
So that is going to
activate macrophages.
You're going to get
pro-inflammatory
cytokines being released.
So TNF-alpha, IL-1, things
like that, that are going
to induce inflammation,
in addition to the cell
necrosis, right, the cell
death that's going to be
brought about by lymphocytes.
So cytotoxic T cells,
natural killer cells
that are beginning
to identify the virally
infected myocytes.
Now, if you take a step
back and take a look at
it from a worldwide
picture, and really that
means more or less central
and South America. The
main microbial agent is
going to be the parasitic
infection trypanosoma
cruzi, and trypanosoma
cruzi causes a condition
known as Chagas disease.
So the parasite is going
to be vectored by a bug,
which is known as the reduvid
bug, and you can track
the parasite when the bug
takes a blood meal. So the
parasite will enter into
the bloodstream in its
trypomastigote form, which
is what you can see in the
microscopic blood smear on
the slide. And the parasite
will then target muscle
tissue. And as it invades
the muscle tissue, it will
convert to its amastigote
form and then multiply. And
so you would imagine that
this will also evoke an
immune response leading to
inflammation and then also
has the ability to lead
to myocyte death or muscle
destruction as well all
right now myocarditis is going
to be much less frequently
caused by bacterial
infections but there is one
correlation to make here
with Lyme disease which is
caused by a bacterial
infection and is also something
frequently seen in the
northeastern United States.
So Lyme disease is caused
by the bacterium Borrelia
burgdorferi, which
morphologically is a spirochete.
And you can see an image
of the cells on the slide.
Now, Borrelia as an
infection is going
to be vectored by
ticks. So to get Lyme
disease, you have to
be bitten by a tick.
And at that location, that
is going to be where the
infection is localized.
Now, Lyme disease is going
to progress through three
basic stages, and right
at the beginning, the local
infection, what you're
going to see is erythema
migrans at the site of the
tick bite, which essentially
is a rash, classically
in the bullseye pattern
like you see on the slide.
Now, if left untreated,
the bacteria can move
through the bloodstream and
the lymph and disseminate
throughout the body.
Now, this is where you can
have complications from
the infection. So,
complications in the CNS. You
could have secondary
rashes that are going to
develop because of that.
And this is where you can
have cardiac involvement
as well. So, AV block,
where the bacterial
infection is now disrupting
the electrical signaling
in the heart. and
then also this is where
you can have myocarditis
develop because of that
bacterial infection.
Now in terms of Lyme disease
if again left untreated
it could move over the
course of months to years
to stage three where you
could have more chronic issues
certainly seen in the
CNS and then also the
targeting of joints will
lead to the potential for
arthritis because of bacterial
infection and of course
this can all be dealt with
relatively easily just by
utilizing antibiotics early
on in the course of infection
so the clinical manifestation
of myocarditis is
going to be somewhat
variable so some individuals
are going to be completely
asymptomatic where other
patients are going to
have just generalized
generalized symptoms, a group
of generalized symptoms,
almost mirroring something
like the flu. So fever
and just general systemic
symptoms. If there's
chest pain involved due to
the myocyte necrosis and
ischemia, you could use
an ECG to rule out an MI.
Myocarditis, generally
speaking, is rarely going to
be fulminant, meaning
that it's rarely going to
proceed to a very extreme
case that's going to become
life-threatening usually
myocarditis certainly
viral myocarditis is going
to be somewhat self-limiting
generally it'll result
in full recovery with
really no long-term
complications if there is chronic
myocarditis usually it
has the potential to lead
to then some sort of
ventricular dysfunction and
ultimately has the potential
to lead to heart failure
Now, the DALS criteria
is a system of
classification used to
diagnose myocarditis,
and it requires an
endomyocardial biopsy.
Now, the tissue has to
show two things. Number
one, an inflammatory
infiltrate into the myocardium,
and then the associated
necrosis of the myocytes
or some sort of degradation
of the myocytes.
Now, on the right-hand
side, you could see
two histological images,
one of normal myocardium,
normal myocytes,
and then a second
histological image that
has active myocarditis.
And on the left-hand side,
you could see an example,
again, of the myocardium
from a section that is
virally infected, viral
myocarditis, and you could
see the significant
lymphocytic infiltrate into it.
So, the initial workup
is going to include
an ECG and troponins
to rule out an MI in
addition to blood count
and some lab tests to
identify inflammatory
markers and an echo.
A CMR image is the kind of
gold standard non-invasive
test and you can see that
off to the right hand
side, whereas the gold
standard diagnostic test is
going to revolve around
the endomyocardial biopsy.
Now, that's required to
be able to meet the Dallas
criteria and to be able
to definitively diagnose
myocarditis, but that
really wouldn't be necessary
except in very extreme
life-threatening cases.
So generally speaking, if
myocarditis is presumed
to be the issue, the
treatments and interventions
are really going to be
individualized for the
particular patient based on
their own clinical context.
All right, so we're going
to move on here, moving
from the inside of the heart
to the outside of the heart.
We're going to take a
look at pericarditis, and
pericarditis is basically
just a generalized term for
inflammation associated
with the pericardium, and
that is the sac around your
heart. Now, that structure
has two basic layers to
it. So there's an external
fibrous layer, the fibrous
pericardium, and then there's
an internal serous
pericardial layer, which is
itself two membranes. It's
a double membrane layer that
has a cavity in the middle
that holds somewhere in
the order of approximately
50 milliliters of fluid.
Now, the pericardium
also is going to have
some functionality
to it, right? So it's
going to help with
cardiac efficiency.
It'll help distribute
pressure and
hydrostatic forces
around the heart.
It obviously creates a
closed chamber, and that
chamber is going to have
pressure that is different
than atmospheric pressure,
which is going to help
with chamber fillings,
specifically the atria.
It's a structure
that protects the
heart from any
type of friction.
It's a barrier against
infection. infection
and then obviously it
also has some anatomical
function to it where
it helps to place
and fix the heart
within the chest cavity.
All right so typically
cases of pericarditis
are going to be idiopathic
and while sometimes
the exact cause is not
going to be known oftentimes
it's going to be
presumed that the case is
going to be tied to some
sort of immune system
dysfunction or some
sort of viral infection.
In the case of viral
pericarditis, the infection
is typically going to
be self-limiting and is
rarely going to be fatal.
Now if we take a look
at some of the viral
causes, they certainly
mirror those that we saw
in myocarditis as well
with NR viruses like
Coxsackie viruses being the
most common typical
agent that you would see.
But then other common
viruses as well,
like adenoviruses
or the flu, COVID,
different varieties of
herpes viruses, among others.
All right, now, while
viral infections are
the overall leading
cause of pericarditis,
you can also have a
bacterial infection.
That might be a little
less common, but it has
potential to be a little
bit more dangerous. In that
case, the typical common
causative agents in
areas of the world like
North America and Europe
are going to be strep
pneumoniae and staph aureus.
Now, if you have these
bacterial species
causing pericarditis,
it would then be
referred to as
purulent pericarditis.
So the way these bacteria
can access the pericardium
could be just through
the bloodstream, could
be direct extension
maybe from pneumonia, or
maybe rare cases following
a surgical procedure.
All right, now if we consider
the most common cause
globally in that case, then
mycobacterium tuberculosis
would be the most common
cause of pericarditis. and
in that case, generally
speaking, it's going to produce
a subacute chronic form of
pericarditis. Of course,
this is going to be the
causative agent of tuberculosis
and so this would be the
most common cause in any
area of the world where
tuberculosis is also endemic.
Now lastly, you could also
have fungi being the cause
of pericarditis, although
it would be somewhat rare.
So different types
of fungi like candida
or aspergillus or
histoplasma could be the
microbial cause of
it if it is a fungus.
So what are we looking for in
a patient with pericarditis?
So one of the main symptoms
is going to be chest pain.
And that pain generally is
going to be worse when the
patient is inhaling or lying
down. And so oftentimes
individuals with pericarditis
are going to want to sit
up or lean forward to be
able to alleviate that pain.
You might also see generalized
symptoms like a fever
or other just, you know,
constitutional symptoms as
well, in addition to something
known as a friction rub.
And a friction rub is kind of
a hallmark of pericarditis.
What that is, it's basically
a high-pitched, scratchy
sound that's generated
by the inflamed layers of
the pericardium that are
rubbing against each other.
Now, during your workup,
you might also use other
diagnostic tests, like
an ECG, where you might
see changes in the PR or
the ST segments, and you
might also use imaging
as well. So what you're
looking for there is
some sort of pericardial
effusion, so more fluid
entering into that pericardial
space, and you might
be able to see that on
an echo or a CMR imaging
or with a chest x-ray.
And what you're looking
for is basically just
an enlargement of the
cardiac silhouette,
like you can see on
the image on the slide.
All right, so
let's consider some
complications to pericarditis.
So the first one will
continue with the concept of
pericardial effusion,
right? So as the fluid
increases within the
pericardial space, so as you get
more fluid there, what's
going to happen is the
pressure is going to increase,
and that higher pericardial
pressure is referred to
as cardiac tamponade.
So as you get more
pressure, that's going to
compress the heart more.
And then ultimately,
because of that
compression, you're going to
get a decreased cardiac
output because of it.
Now, another complication
is constrictive
pericarditis. And this is going
to be a result really
of inflammation.
So chronic inflammation
that leads to fibrosis
and calcification
of the pericardium.
pericardium. So if the
pericardium is becoming
more rigid, it's not
going to expand as much.
And then obviously, you're
going to get a smaller
blood volume and a decrease
in ventricular filling
because of that. Now, this
is certainly going to be a
potential complication of
tuberculosis, where you have
mycobacterium tuberculosis
causing, being the common
cause of subacute chronic
forms of pericarditis.
Now, in general, in
terms of treatment, the
treatment is really going
to depend on what the
causative agent of that
pericarditis would be.
And so if we're talking
about a viral cause,
then, you know, probably
just symptom management
and some supportive
care would be enough.
If instead you have a
bacterial or a fungal
source, then using
antimicrobial agents
would certainly be the
best bet, in addition
to generalized anti
-inflammatories. So
that concludes the
lecture. I just wanted
to thank everyone
for listening, and I
wanted to provide the
link for feedback.
Thank you.